A woman: ...7 in the book.
Dr. Khalifa: Page 46.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Sura 92, The Night.
In the name of GOD, Most Gracious, Most Merciful.
[92:1]  By the night as it covers.
[92:2]  The day as it reveals.
[92:3]  And Him who created the male and the female.
[92:4]  Your works are of various kinds.
[92:5]  As for him who gives to charity and maintains righteousness.
[92:6]  And upholds the scripture.
[92:7]  We will direct him towards happiness.
[92:8]  But he who is stingy, though he is rich.
[92:9]  And disbelieves in the scripture.
[92:10]  We will direct him towards misery.
[92:11]  His money cannot help him when he falls.
[92:12]  We provide the guidance.
[92:13]  We control the Hereafter, as well as this life.
[92:14]  I have warned you about the blazing Hellfire.
[92:15]  None burns therein except the wicked.
[92:16]  Who disbelieves and turns away.
[92:17]  Avoiding it will be the righteous.
[92:18]  Who gives from his money to charity.
[92:19]  Seeking nothing in return.
[92:20]  Seeking only his Lord, the Most High.
[92:21]  He will certainly attain salvation.
Verse 1 and verse 2.
[92:1]  By the night as it covers.
[92:2]  The day as it reveals.
There are many, many verses which refer to
day, night, forenoon, and dawn.
The night is created for our rest and therefore
is a benefit.
And we can use that as an analogy to this life because we're blocked from being in God's presence while we're in this life.
It is a sort of darkness. It is a sort of barrier.
We cannot stand God's presence in our present
form.
[92:2]  The day as it reveals.
Most of the references in Quran about day
are about the Day of Resurrection all the way through.
And I thought of that as an analogy to life
which reveals the truth and things as they are.
And I thought that appropriate too, when we consider
the Day of Resurrection, the Day of Judgment,
because that's, in fact, what will happen.
We're all familiar with this night and how black
it can be without any stars or the moon out.
I used to live up on a hill in the middle
of the country and there was no electricity from house to house.
There's nothing to see except the lightning
bugs if you were fortunate.
You couldn't see your hand in front of your
face.
It was that dark.
And that's quite a cover.
It removes our world from us so that what
we remember of the world in the daylight really is an illusion.
The night takes everything away and that's
what happened to us when we had to come to this life.
We had to be away from our real life for the
period of time we're here.
And when the sun comes up and things begin
to take shape, the first thing that we see is silhouettes usually.
I live across the street from a park now and
when the sun rises, the trees don't have any texture or depth of color.
They're shapes as the sun begins to come up.
And they look flat.
And as the sun rises further, the color appears and then its depth and texture and you see individual leaves moving and all the parts that make up the tree.
And so the day is revelation and the Day of
Judgment is a revelation to all of us,
even those of us who hope to be safe on the
Day of Resurrection.
I think we will also see things that we did
not see ever in this lifetime.
[92:3]  And Him who created the male and the female.
[92:4]  Your works are of various kinds.
Some time ago, I went through Quran and looked
for all of the references that God made to the human being,
whether it was about creation or about our
nature and our characters.
And there are an awful lot, as I was telling
Lydia before we started, an awful lot of descriptions of us
that are not real positive. We're hasty, we're unappreciative, contentious, parsimonious,
and unappreciative is throughout quite a bit.
And there are rare instances where the verse might finish with the phrase "except for those who lead a righteous life" or something similar.
Our works are of various kinds. And for those of us who do things that appear to be Quranic but we are still involved in idol worship,
we know that those works are nullified. And
in fact, God designs those works to help others.
We are all in the service of each other but that on the Day of Resurrection, if we are involved in idol worship, they will be as if we had not done them.
Verses 5 through 11 describe two types of
people.
God alone knows what each of our choice was,
what in our hearts we really believe even though
we forgot when we came here.
For those of us who chose God alone, God willing all of us, God will give us everything in our life to augment that choice.
We know those things as tests.
We know them as gifts. We know them as miracles. We each have stories to tell.
And as we recognize them as such, they augment and cement and increase our faith and our knowledge in God's truth and His guarantees.
For those who do not believe, God also provides
for them what they need to continue disbelief.
It may appear as though they're wondrous
things for instance they're very wealthy or people
that have great status or people that seem
to have a lot of power and can get people
in countries to do things for themselves, for
instance.
Those people may consider themselves blessed,
but God is merely continuing to test them
so that at the end, at the Day of Judgment,
there will be no excuse whatsoever.
Nothing they can say or do except to ask to come back and try again which, of course, we know will not be allowed.
So, I read those verses as descriptions of
how God is so Merciful to all of us
because even though God knows the choice of the disbelievers
and augments that choice in their life,
He still is providing proof of God alone and
the truth to them
in the midst of all the things that are given and all the things that
seem to be provided so easily.
What I thought was that I constantly think
that this life is an illusion it is one huge test
for all of us, believers or not, and we have to keep striving to find the truth to be believers with certainty and that's very difficult.
Sometimes some of the things that God causes
to happen in our lives,
the people we meet, the settings we find ourselves in are confusing
and they can make us wonder if we're on the right path at all.
But that is in fact the
test that we have to keep striving and stay
right where we're going toward God alone and
whatever is puzzling will become clear very quickly if we do that.
Does anybody have any comments, questions,
additions, up till here?
Okay.
[92:12]  We provide the guidance.
[92:13]  We control the Hereafter, as well as this life.
God controls all things.
We speak of the words we utter, we think that they're our own, we think that the thoughts that we have are our own and we know that they aren't.
God knows ahead of time what we're going to
say and the effect that our words are going to have on other people.
More than that
[92:13]  We control the Hereafter, as well as this life.
Our lives are so perfectly designed.
We have all the choices in the world available
to us.
What time we're going to get up for Salat
in the morning, we choose that time
unless we wake up and don't need an alarm clock anymore
like Rashad.
We choose what we're gonna have for breakfast
whether we're gonna eat at all.
We choose how we're gonna get to work, we
choose what time, we choose what we're going
to do when we get there, we choose how to prioritize
the tasks in a day we think,
we have an awful lot of control over our lives, what we're going
to wear, what we're going to do when we come home
that night, we make plans with the people
in our lives, relatives, friends.
All of that is designed for us. We have no choice at all
in reality.
All of that is a test and it's designed specifically,
individually for each person in the world.
The money we earn is already predetermined.
To worry about it is foolish.
We know that God is Merciful and provides
relief in every situation
including the amount of money that we need. And all of us have stories about some great need arising and not having
the faintest idea in the world how we were
going to accomplish it, and
suddenly, there was money from somewhere unexplained.
Our relatives, those people that are part of our family, mother, father, aunts, uncles, cousins, they were chosen for us also.
For some of us, we are distanced from our family
because of our choice to believe in God alone,
but that's also part of our test. We were assigned
to their household as our children were assigned to our own.
Those people that become friends of ours, those people that we find ourselves working with, whether we like them or not, were put there by God for us.
I've talked before about working in a hospital
and part of my job is to take care of patients.
They're assigned a person like myself when
they come into the hospital and we think that somebody
there assigns Joe Smith to Catherine,
in fact God does that and allows me to meet
some people and not others that come through
the hospital for a reason.
Material things that we gain or do not gain
are again designed by God
to test whether we're focused on the need for those or not, amongst other things the environmental settings that we find ourselves in.
I remember traveling to the conference and
Rashad telling that story about the bugs
at that time that we stopped to make Salat
and made it the fastest we'd ever made it before.
All of us were destined to do that. We didn't
know that. We didn't know that was going to happen.
And it was on green grass, as I remember,
in the middle of the desert.
It was a nice carpet of grass and Rashad was right where there was no grass. He just seemed to be waiting for all of us.
He certainly was.
But for some reason all of us were to share
that experience and run
back to the van, I remember going back to the van. We didn't stay there very long.
All the things that are designed in our lives whether they're people or things or places we travel to, they're all designed
by God. And in all of them is the proof of
God alone and that God controls all things.
If we are truly searching for that, we'll see that in all things, in all conversations, in all the people that we meet, all the places that we go.
If we know that God controls everything and
there are layers and layers of that.
When we first begin to understand that God controls
everything, it's confusing
because you wanna say "well, wait a minute, I, I chose that and
I chose this" and, and then, the realization comes
that God controls everything and you didn't choose it. But you still retain the thought that what's in your head is your own.
Out there is ok, God's running all of that,
but your thoughts are your own and you're using your mind to
understand that and then the next layer peels away
and you realize that the thoughts you
have in your head are not even your own.
They're part of a perfectly designed life for each
of us. And in those lives, the truth is buried
everywhere. In fact, it's not buried, it's so
obvious and the more layers we peel away and
the more understanding we come to have about
the reason we're here and what God is doing
for us in His Great Mercy and Graciousness
to us, it becomes as if everything floats to
the surface. The world looks very very different.
Jason just bought a car and I was telling Rashad
this the other day, he had to buy it
because it had a big 19 all over it but that's another story.
And we were talking about him
driving on the road with him being just 16,
his mother saying to myself "I really hope God
means it when He says He's gonna protect everybody" from Jason.
And we were talking, and we were talking and I said
"you know, I often drive to work and I think of all of the things, the creatures that are driving along with me."
It's not just the cars as bumper to bumper, but it's every person
in every car has a jinn riding with them
and two angels one on the right and one on the
left, and it's a wonder there's any room on the road for the car,
when you think about that, but all those other people driving along looking right and left as if they don't know that.
They've no idea how much protection is involved in those near misses when somebody turns left and we can see the angel right there.
We can't, but we can, we know the angel
was there to avoid this crash.
So, world takes on a very different perspective and, Alhamdu Lillah, a great peace occurs
when we understand that what seems bad is in that
God is after us in Mercy
and to provide the guidance that we need to find Him and return
to Him and never be separated again it's really incredible.
A woman: Are there any comments about those
two verses?
Dr. Khalifa: Finish the Sura.
A woman: No.
Dr. Khalifa: You're doing so well.
A woman: Rashad, you have any comments at all?
Dr. Khalifa: You finished.
A woman: Yes.
A woman: Ok.
[92:14]  I have warned you about the blazing Hellfire.
[92:15]  None burns therein except the wicked.
[92:16]  Who disbelieves and turns away.
That's very straight forward. God gives many descriptions in Quran about the types of people that are going to end up in Hell.
And some of them are almost abstract.
This is very straight forward and it's a bottom line.
People who disbelieve and turn away are
wicked and there is no second chance.
Hell is where these people will be and they don't
know it. They won't know it until the Day of Resurrection.
[92:17]  Avoiding it will be the righteous.
[92:18]  Who gives from his money to charity.
[92:19]  Seeking nothing in return.
[92:20]  ... only his Lord, the Most High.
[92:21]  He will certainly attain salvation.
The righteous are spared with the greatest mercy because
we know that we've all sinned.
For those of us who mercifully come to understand God alone and
free ourselves from any type of idol worship including our own ego,
this is a tremendous accomplishment. It's described as such with words in Quran but I don't think we can fully understand
how much mercy from God is involved here for us to escape even to end up in Purgatory hanging on by our toenails would be an incredible mercy.
And then, God again very simply describes
those people who are going to avoid Hell for all eternity
and those are people who are not really attached to this world, who understand that what is part of their life
is, is given. It is all a gift from God.
And it is not meant that we should keep every single thing that
comes our way and to think of anything as ours
is also foolish because it's God's. And if we're meant to give it away then we should do that without ever looking back.
One of the difficulties I had in my family being raised as a Christian, we had to go through that Christmas fantasy that happens for months every year.
And in my family from the time I was very
young, the giving of gifts never was the giving of gifts,
it was always attached to conditions
even though everyone knew, for instance, that
we had three small children and didn't have
a lot of money and the gifts were given with
great smiles, there was always the great frown
and the comments that similar gifts were not given in return.
And if they weren't, it was
remembered from year to year to year to year, forever.
And finally, long before I moved to
Tucson, Alhamdu Lillah, I just told my family
"we don't do Christmas anymore. I don't know what
it is anymore. I don't know what you think you're doing,
"but I cannot participate in it. I cannot encourage my children to do this."
This is, this is just horrible. You don't know how to
give anything. My family would come to help,
and the help was more of a burden because
there were strings attached to that, something that we were,
we were supposed to do or behave
or perform. God says that for those of us who are
true believers, we recognize that, that
what we have is to be shared with the people around us,
because it's given to us for that
purpose to overcome our natural need to be
stingy and to hoard is also a tremendous accomplishment.
It's almost impossible.
I was in the, finally up in the DeGrazia Gallery, recently. I didn't
know where it was and hadn't heard of this man forever.
And a guest came down from Phoenix
and she had wanted to go, so we drove up there,
walked around in the last 20 minutes of the
day and there are pictures on the wall, I don't know
how many of you have been up there, some
of them are the little girls, the Indian girls
that we all recognize as DeGrazia's work
but he did a lot of other things so there's
oil paintings on the wall and so are the prices
of these paintings.
And I cannot imagine someone paying $2,000 for a painting never mind more than that and there were many for $2,000 $4,000.
And as Lisa walked around, at one point, I heard
her, we were alone, it was almost toward the end of it, closing.
And she, she put her hands on
her hips and she looked in the glass display
case also with items, price tags attached and
said to herself
"I would hope that if I had that much money, I would give it to charity
and I would not buy this painting or this (unintelligible)."
And I looked at her and I thought "dead on, she doesn't know much about Islam, but that's the way we need to be.
"To have that kind of money and not think about using it to help others is a sin." And there are many people like that as we know.
The last two verses tell us what we get and God always gives a
guarantee, seeking only our Lord, the Most High.
If we stay focused on that and not this material world, accepting so far as we are to behave righteously and we are giving guidelines for that,
he will certainly obtain salvation. This is a guarantee. There's no question at all. And there are many such guarantees in Quran,
if we but follow God's instructions. The
path can at times seem extraordinarily narrow
and at other times so wide because we feel
so protected, those angels seem to grow before our eyes.
Fortunately, we don't try to fly without wings, but it's almost that
wonderful, that kind of peace.
And then the tests come again as the purification process
continues.
If we stay focused on God alone and we manage to pass those tests, that we are sincere in our hearts, Salvation means eternal life, or we're alive.
There's nothing that we could possibly want in this world that's more than that, or better than that or equal to it.
A woman: Now, does anybody have comments?
Dr. Khalifa: Edip
A woman: Good
Edip: (unintelligible)
Edip: For example, if you (unintelligible) night and day then, you are
Edip: Then, give an example also (unintelligible)
that gives, gives charity, and the other one is stingy.
Edip: (unintelligible)
Edip: Then, the wicked and the righteous.
Edip: There are seven (unintelligible), seven...
Edip: (unintelligible)
Edip: Quran says,
Edip: (unintelligible) Quran is a...
(39:23) مُّتَشَٰبِهًۭا مَّثَانِىَ
Edip: Explains in both ways.
A man: Yes.
Edip: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Not exactly. (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Contrasts.
Edip: Yes.
A man: Why the contrast? Why did not (unintelligible)
Edip: (unintelligible). Our life is based on contrast.
Everything we can see, there is opposite.
And by this struggle between the opposite things, or changing, rotation between the opposite things, we see life, everything,
days, and nights, (unintelligible), beautiful, ugly, small, big, everything we can... poverty, (unintelligible).
Edip: And if we can see a good person, a bad person,
a good person life, a day, a bad person life, night (unintelligible).
Edip: (unintelligible)
A man: (unintelligible)
A man: I have a question. Why the three first, first three verses, our God is swearing
[92:1]  By the night ...
[92:2]  The day ...
[92:3]  And ... male and ... female.
(unintelligible)
[92:4]  Your works are of various kinds.
Why, why three verses, God is swearing to these
three, although they are coming in contrast,
(unintelligible)
creation, life, and being.
It doesn't matter if you have (unintelligible) anything. Then,
[92:4]  Your works are of various kinds.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, we have three. We have three profound introductions.
Dr. Khalifa: The day and the night are profound signs,
as you know.
They remind us that the earth is hanging in
space, and the male and the female.
So, these three profound verses tell us that...
actually, this short Sura tells the secret of happiness.
So, it is very important to know which path
will lead you to happiness, in this world and forever,
and which path will lead you
to misery, in this world and forever.
So, you see in verse 7, the path to happiness.
Sura 54, if you remember, God says, He directs you to happiness or misery. He controls that.
It is now established that material success
does not bring happiness.
So,
[92:4]  Your works are of various kinds.
And they will lead you to either path, happiness or misery.
And what I wanted to emphasize is verses 5
and 18. Both of them talk about charity.
In this short Sura, two verses talk about
charity, because it's a continuous process.
Just like we feed, God wants to remind us that, just because we continuously feed our body, how many times did you drink today?
You drank water or coke or something today.
You drank, you ate, you really take care of
your body, your garment.
So, God is reminding us to take care of the
real person, of you.
To take care of you is a continuous process,
just like the eating, and the drinking, and the sleeping,
and the showering, the things that you do for your body, is a continuous process, and like the five Contact Prayers,
continuous process, Charity also is a continuous process, because
you continuously make money.
You have to set aside 2.5% for your relatives,
your parents, and so on, as the Quran directs.
The three verses, three profound signs, this is common in the short Suras, precede something that's very important.
And here, the important thing is the secret of
happiness.
Dr. Khalifa: If you do these continuous processes, that
develop your soul, God promises you, happiness now and forever.
Edip: So, these three verses are consistent with
the, with the text, because in verse 4,
[92:4]  Your works are of various kinds.
Dr. Khalifa: Contrasting.
Edip: Yes, (unintelligible)
Edip: And then, the Hereafter (unintelligible).
A man: Why, why (unintelligible) charity (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Because people neglect to do it.
Dr. Khalifa: It's not only in this Sura. Actually, if you look in almost every Sura, you see it.
Edip: Especially, Rashad, especially in Meccan Suras, chapters, in
short chapters, you can find...
Dr. Khalifa: In almost every Sura, we have something about
charity.
Edip: But in short chapters, the average percentage
of the charity is more.
Dr. Khalifa: It's something that people tend to forget,
to neglect.
In fact, I keep repeating, so I remind myself.
I need to remind myself, not to be lax in
doing it.
So every time, we receive money, we just have
to cut out 2.5%.
It's a very good investment.
The reason God repeats it is because God knows
that we tend to forget, or neglect to do it.
We seem to do the five daily Prayers easily.
Charity is something that we tend to forget, because we get involved in spending. Before you know it, your money is gone.
We didn't set aside the 2.5%.
Dr. Khalifa: So, the reason this is... also, repetition is, is psychologically important.
A man: (unintelligible) This is a comment.
A man: Since God knows the human being (unintelligible), we're Praying, we Pray because, you know, it doesn't cost you anything.
A man: (unintelligible)
A man: But giving money, (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Also, it has to be a continuous process just like eating and drinking.
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible)
A woman: (unintelligible), in looking up about charity (unintelligible)
the verse, the verse (unintelligible) in chapter 2
say that you give from the
money you earned.
A woman: Does that mean, say, if you're given money that you didn't work for? I know it would be better if you gave from it, but do you have to give?
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, any money you earn, you earn whether you work
for it or not, any money that you make.
Dr. Khalifa: Any money that enters your pocket and becomes
yours.
Dr. Khalifa: Anybody else? Questions? 93.
A man: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Hmm?
A man: If you loan money...
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A man: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: The loan money is supposed to happen during (unintelligible).
Dr. Khalifa: In other words, you receive $500, you take 2.5%, and then somebody wants $300, you will loan the $300, your $300 is already purified.
The money is purified only once.
Dr. Khalifa: Who's waving here? Hi!
A woman: Do people have to pay charity money on charity money (unintelligible)?
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Dr. Khalifa: Because, because every person knows some, some other people who will need assistance.
It is based on personal knowledge.
This is why God gave you that sequence, your parents, your relatives, the orphans, the poor, the needy, the alien.
It's based on personal knowledge.
And we read in Sura 2 that there are people
who may need it and nobody will know.
Dr. Khalifa: But people close to them will know. Go ahead.
A woman: But (unintelligible)
A woman: I was at work (unintelligible)
a phone call (unintelligible) this person that was (unintelligible) person
(unintelligible) for a whole day. (unintelligible)
A woman: It was (unintelligible) and it was right (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: But God was helping you. Yes.
A woman: Yes.
Dr. Khalifa: So, (unintelligible). It's based on personal knowledge.
Dr. Khalifa: Sura 93, (unintelligible)
A woman: (unintelligible)
[93:3]  Your Lord never abandoned you, nor did He forget.
[93:4]  The Hereafter is far better for you than this first (life).
[93:5]  And your Lord will give you enough; you will be pleased.
[93:6]  Did He not find you orphaned and He gave you a home?
[93:7]  He found you astray, and guided you.
[93:8]  He found you poor, and made you rich.
[93:9]  Therefore, you shall not forsake the orphan.
[93:10]  Nor shall you reprimand the beggar.
[93:11]  You shall proclaim the blessing your Lord has bestowed upon you.
It seems to be almost a repetition, and again,
preceded by the same profound phrases.
[93:1]  By the forenoon.
which is the brightest part
of the day, and
[93:2]  By the night as it falls.
[93:3]  Your Lord never abandoned you, ...
Closer to us than our jugular vein is the
phrase that all of us remember.
We have constant companions recording but
also protecting us.
Psalm 91 talks about the angels protecting
us lest we dash our foot against a stone.
There's a popular kind of poem, I guess, it's
called Footprints that You See Out,
and the man questions why in the worst part of his
life he only saw one set of footprints in the sand,
and was almost accusing God of not keeping His promise, that God lets him get all of that out and then says,
those were the
times that I carried you.
I think that's directed at Jesus and I can't
remember now but the truth of it is profound.
We are never alone in the worst of times ever
and we are protected.
Edip never once got stopped by a policeman
on that trip.
We are protected.
Even, even something like that.
I mean, that just was amazing.
[93:4]  The Hereafter is far better for you than this first (life).
The Hereafter is our quest.
There are so many stories and movies that
are what I call quest movies.
There's always some goal to be strived for and great sacrifices and great dangers on the way to the prize, whatever it may be.
But that's what we're doing.
Our whole lives are a quest and there are great dangers and many distractions and many provisions along the way.
We have to remember that this life is not
the goal, and that's very hard.
There are so many distractions in our day. So many. A phone call.
Just as you're starting to think about what to do with the (unintelligible) for that week, you get a phone call. The beeper goes off.
Somebody comes in your office. Somebody calls you and the thought goes.
And it doesn't come back maybe for hours.
And you have to say "who was your god for
that day?"
"How many minutes did you retain that thought
throughout all the things that you do during the day?"
Our quest is to focus on getting ourselves
safely to the Hereafter to be with God.
And a guarantee.
[93:5]  And your Lord will give you enough; you will be pleased.
I have no idea what that means.
I have absolutely no idea what that means.
A woman: I have so much that's enough in my life. Everything. I have enough of everything right now.
Dr. Khalifa: But this is it. This is what it means.
A woman: But enough in the Hereafter.
Dr. Khalifa: No, this is here.
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible)
A woman: And in the Hereafter. I mean, the two things are incomprehensible to us.
[93:5]  ... you will be pleased.
is an understatement.
And then, the question we were discussing a
moment ago.
[93:6]  Did He not find you orphaned ... gave you a home?
[93:7]  ... astray, and guided you.
[93:8]  ... poor, and made you rich.
God provides for all creatures.
Rashad talked about the sunflowers and the
ants that crawl under them. And the alligators in Florida.
All of them with hearts beating. All of them needing food, nutrients. The system is incredible.
It is such a complex interlocking system,
right down to the tiniest cell and its components,
which we are down to quarks at this point.
Everything has its provisions.
We don't know how to do that. We're still...
I drove the other day to work and there was
a young man setting up a tripod with a surveying instrument on it.
And I watched him. He was walking, walking down the road,
not flying in a jet convoy, but still walking
with a tripod,
the same kind of, I don't know, George Washington
used or Galileo used,
peering through a tube to establish a straight eye
And I thought, we've come so far and we've
done nothing.
We've just done nothing. We're still walking.
We're, we're still walking.
Surely, there's another way from a satellite or something to do what he had to do by walking and setting up this awkward instrument.
Provisions for all things.
[93:9]  Therefore, you shall not forsake the orphan.
[93:10]  Nor shall you reprimand the beggar.
[93:11]  You shall proclaim the blessing your Lord has bestowed upon you.
There's a Sura, I'm sorry I don't know
the number where Muhammad is told not to ignore
those that come to him that appear not to
be perhaps as wealthy or as well-situated as others.
I think he was chastised for ignoring a person
like that and tending to someone else over him.
We don't know other people's choices.
We have no idea what their eventual choice,
their eventual place is going to be in the Eternal Life.
And it's not for us to judge.
It is for us to forsake the material world
and hence our own egos, our own bodies
that we pay so much attention to and take care of the world around us. For all we know these are our family, our real family.
And we wouldn't know that. We have no way of knowing that.
[93:11]  You shall proclaim the blessing your Lord has bestowed upon you.
Mã Shã Allãh. Alhamdu Lillah.
IN SHAA ALLAH.
Be careful how we speak of God. It came to mind
because Rashad talked to us one day about
being careful how we spoke about God.
God does not make us sick.
We make ourselves sick. God heals.
We used, I think you used this example of Moses
and his teacher.
And each one of those examples, it was the
human being that made the error and God that made it right.
So, we need to proclaim God's blessing to us.
We don't need to say to each other "well, God
made that tire flat" and leave it there.
We need to understand what we're saying. We need to be real careful. If the tire's flat, we did something.
God will help us get the tire fixed so the
car will go again.
And it really is that simple and that complex
at the same time.
Words come out of our mouths very quickly. We don't think about them.
Sometimes we just speak.
And we need to be careful. I've taught myself any number of times after that (unintelligible)
stopping in the middle of a sentence or a word and rephrasing it because we understand that God runs and controls all things.
He allows the things to happen that
need to happen for us.
So, it's very easy to make a mistake, cross over the line and say "I'm sick because God wanted me to be sick for this reason."
That's not it.
So, we need to be very careful and only talk
about the good things that God does.
Comments?
A woman: David!
David: Remember (unintelligible) I have like somebody's request (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: You don't know his circumstances.
David: Yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: There are times when able-bodied people with perfect
qualifications somehow they just go weeks,
Dr. Khalifa: maybe months without, without a job. They just don't
seem to be able...
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: You have to be extremely kind to them.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, I agree.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: The fact is there may be exceptions.
Dr. Khalifa: Some professional beggars, there are (unintelligible)
Audience: (unintelligible)
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, it could be.
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible)
A woman: (unintelligible)
A woman: Well, (unintelligible)
A woman: I know (unintelligible)
A man: (unintelligible)
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: That's a different issue, though, begging.
You have to use your discretion.
Dr. Khalifa: Remember, you cannot be suspicious. We have to know.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: In Tucson, it's the food bank.
Dr. Khalifa: In Tucson, it's the food bank. But sometimes you meet these people in the street or they come to your door.
You have to act.
There's a commandment here not to reprimand
the beggar.
So, you'd better be careful. I'd rather be a sucker than...
Dr. Khalifa: And the (unintelligible) is commanded.
A woman: Yeah. (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Right. Right. But I mean, this is the least...
Dr. Khalifa: The least you can do is not reprimand the person, of course, unless you know personally what he or she is doing.
A woman: (unintelligible)
A man: (unintelligible)
A man: I don't know. If I can't think of any (unintelligible)
A woman: (unintelligible)
A woman: I think they're doing a great job (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: You have to start with the surroundings, so, your parents, your relatives.
Dr. Khalifa: And if there's somebody here at the mosque
that needs it, that will be, you take priority over...
A woman: So, it takes priority over...
Dr. Khalifa: A children's organization probably takes a
lot of money from United Way.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: And they have a lot of professionals living
off of that, too.
I investigate. I find that the food bank is very clean.
They don't have shysters, organizers.
And they really do give food to the poor. So, this is...
There are some other organizations that take
millions of dollars,
the homes for the children abused, battered
wires, abused this and that.
United Way pays the millions of dollars, and there are organizers and administrators who take up to 90% of that money. (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: So, you're paying salaries.
A woman: (unintelligible) I volunteer (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, there's nothing wrong with what they're doing.
A woman: There's nothing wrong, there's nothing wrong with giving that.
A woman: If you don't use it as (unintelligible) like over and above Zakat to any of those things,
A woman: because I get to a lot of the animal organizations, but I don't count that as Zakat.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, but the system of the Quran is you start with
your own family, and then you go further and further.
Dr. Khalifa: The priorities are set in the Quran. Beth.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Beth. This is something different.
A woman: So, that's why (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: This is your family, too.
A woman: Oh, Ok.
Dr. Khalifa: This is an eternal family right here.
Dr. Khalifa: And occasionally, somebody may lose a job or...
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Dr. Khalifa: Cousins, aunts, uncles, nephews, nieces.
A man: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Dr. Khalifa: I did wanna say it.
A woman: I was gonn.  ask you about the Goodwill.
A woman: The Goodwill.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A woman: That...
Dr. Khalifa: Sure.
A woman: Or like The Salvation Army?
Dr. Khalifa: They should be down in the list.
Dr. Khalifa: Down the list.
A woman: Right, yeah, I know. Yeah.
A woman: You just made the statement about how we should
be really careful of how we think about God,
A woman: and how if we get sick and then we say "God, (unintelligible)"
Dr. Khalifa: Right. You don't attribute sickness to God.
Dr. Khalifa: You don't attribute sickness to God. You attribute it to yourself. Say "I did something wrong."
A woman: Cause I put...
Dr. Khalifa: God is teaching you.
A woman: (unintelligible)
A woman: ...because of diseases. I mean like, because of (unintelligible) consequences.
A woman: For instance, like, I was really sick the other
day. I was really sick.
And the next day, I was feeling, I mean, so
much better. I was fine.
And (unintelligible) I was sick, I (unintelligible)
A woman: And then the following day, (unintelligible), I mean, the thought of (unintelligible).
A woman: ...And was told that sometimes it's to make us more appreciative for all those days, year after year, that we get up and we feel fine.
All those days that we can eat every meal
and it stays down, in me a lot more than in others.
We don't think about that. We take that for granted. We get very caught up in our lives.
And we just swing our feet out of bed and
go to it in the morning.
And do we wake up after we say "Bism Allah Arrahman Arraheem"?
Do we say "look at this, I can get up. There's nothing happening to me. I can get up, I (unintelligible) the floor, everything works.
"I can move, I can walk, I don't trip, I don't
fall. I can smell, I can taste, I can hear."
How many of us do that in the morning?
I, I think it's a miracle that, that my body gets up
and does all those things at 45 years.
I've been doing this for 45 years and there's
no wear and tear here.
A woman: My car runs every day and I have to be grateful
for that, too.
A woman: I didn't look at that as contributing to God's
doing, but I just looked at it constantly as a result of it.
A woman: (unintelligible) because I was supposed to be more (unintelligible)
A woman: Right.
Dr. Khalifa: Also, we have to find out what you did to Edip that...?
Edip: Yes.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: You have to be careful (unintelligible).
A woman: Oh, boy.
A man: Why (unintelligible)? You are always (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: You've been a good, good guest.
A woman: Just beginning.
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
Dr. Khalifa: It hasn't begun yet.
Dr. Khalifa: 94: Cooling the Temper
Mahmoud: I have a question.
Dr. Khalifa: Go, Mahmoud.
Mahmoud: In Sura (unintelligible) Muhammad.
Dr. Khalifa: OK, I'm glad you brought this up. Some people think that this Sura was directed to Muhammad personally because of
[93:5]  ... your Lord will give you ...
[93:6]  Did He not find you orphaned and He gave you a home?
Because Muhammad is an orphan.
[93:7]  He found you astray, and He guided you.
You will not get the Muhammadans to confess
that he ever was astray.
(unintelligible) is laughing because I had my father, he was for four months here and I, I wanted him to say "Muhammad was astray" and he wouldn't say it.
We had lots of funny encounters.
Because when I showed him all the other verses
showing that Muhammad did make mistakes,
he will say "OK, so he was astray."
And then five minutes later, he changes his
mind.
So we...
The way he said "OK, he was astray", but became...
something that would make us laugh every time we remember.
But anyway, "He found you and..." they will not
agree that he was astray.
So, I chose to make the translation general.
[93:8]  He found you poor, and He made you rich.
Because it's applicable to everybody.
If they want to apply it... ironically, most
of them...
almost all of them apply to Muhammad, but they will
not accept verse 7.
Dr. Khalifa: In almost all the Tafseer interpretations,
they interpret this Sura as if God is talking to Muhammad only.
Edip: They misinterpret this verse, verse 7,
a problem, a very big problem for them
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Edip: because their idol becomes, before prophethood, he
was astray.
And then, they want to interpret, one of the
most famous interpretations is,
Edip: "he when, when he was a child, he lost his way (unintelligible)."
Dr. Khalifa: What does it say (unintelligible)
Mahmoud: That's exactly what Rashad says that
he was poor and God made him rich.
Mahmoud: That's exactly what (unintelligible).
Edip:
(93:7) وَوَجَدَكَ ضَآلًّۭا فَهَدَىٰ
Edip: They say "But he lost his way when he was a child."
Mahmoud: How (unintelligible).
Edip: Also, a very short translation, this is the reason.
Mahmoud: No.
Edip: (unintelligible)
Audience: (unintelligible)
A woman: Also, you know, all of us will be orphan
at one time or another, unless we die before our parents do.
A woman: But God always provides the home.
Mahmoud: The reason I'm saying this is that, (unintelligible) that Sura that we have, Cooling the Temper, (unintelligible)
of Muhammad, and all the Suras together (unintelligible)
Mahmoud: Sura that (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yes, (unintelligible)
Also, the next Sura, you do the same thing.
But it can apply to everyone.
Because when you attain... the next Sura,  I'm
sorry, I'm going to the next one, it says,
[94:1]  Did we not cool your temper?
This can apply to any believer, because before
belief, we were excitable, and worries, we were worried, and...
But when you believe, then you put your trust
in God, and you submit, submit to God.
And as submitters, we realize that God knows
what is best for us, and we put everything in God's hands.
Dr. Khalifa: So, we don't worry anymore and you cool your temper.
A man: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: It's, it's, you find that it is not worth it to get angry.
There's nothing in this world that is worth
getting angry at.
Dr. Khalifa: So, this can be also general. So, we go to Catherine and Sura 94.
Catherine: In the name of GOD, Most Gracious, Most Merciful.
[94:1]  Did we not cool your temper?
[94:2]  And we unloaded your load (of sins).
[94:3]  One that burdened your back.
[94:4]  We exalted you to an honorable position.
[94:5]  With pain there is gain.
[94:6]  Indeed, with pain there is gain.
[94:7]  Whenever possible you shall strive.
[94:8]  Seeking only your Lord.
To paraphrase just a little bit on what Rashad
said, although that is the bottom line,
there's nothing in this world that should cause us
to be emotionally involved with it to the point where we're angry.
But even annoyance, a little bit of suspicion.
I remember Rashad giving us the example of
walking past someone on the street, and the
person seemed to be making a face, and we
thought "that person doesn't like me."
That's wrong.
How do we know they don't have a stomachache?
That's helped me a lot in my dealings with
other people, and I work in a place where
I see an awful lot of people who are troubled,
and if I was to, to make,
to be concerned that, perhaps, they didn't like me, or they didn't wanna talk to me, I mean, I, I just, I wouldn't go there at all.
It would be very easy to misinterpret.
On the other hand, if I understand that this
person is part of the family of God,
that I don't know this person's choice, but that
they are to be treated the same, with respect, with dignity,
and in a righteous fashion,
I'm not gonna be angry about anything.
And I, I have to confess a story, another story
here, because these things keep happening.
There is one case that we've been working
on, and in this, this particular case, the person is not...
I was gonna say appropriate, but that sounds
so odd.
The person does not actually belong in our
institution.
The person is developmentally disabled, which
means that this person was retarded since they were born.
And the agency that is supposed to provide
the care for this person has decided not to do so,
and has left the patient in our institution,
which is not a good thing for the, for that patient at all.
And in going to the meetings with many people coming together to decide what to do with this
other person, the other person not present,
of course.
How can we best provide service?
It was clear that there was a lot of politics
going on, and people were trying to avoid spending money,
and so they were literally
dumping the problem in one particular area.
And after the first meeting, I, I remember driving
back to, to the hospital, and I don't even remember the drive back.
I was so incensed at what had happened.
I was so incensed at the dishonesty, at the
manipulation that I had, had witnessed and heard,
and that this person could be so badly mistreated.
It took me a couple of hours to get rid of
what amounted to anger.
I was furious that this person, who is poor,
who cannot fend for himself, has been totally disregarded.
And by the time the two hours was over, I
thought,
I started looking around, cause I was sure the (unintelligible) floor was gonna open up and I was gonna go through it.
I'd wasted two hours being angry at something
that is happening according to God's will and for a reason.
And the person that I was angry for is perfectly
happy where they are, and perfectly well-provided.
And in fact, they're still there.
So, again, we keep learning these lessons.
I wasted a lot of energy, and you can bet
that not once during that two hours was I thinking about God.
It wasn't until I did think about God that
the whole thing went away.
And I had to be sincerely repentant.
So, when we least expect it, those things come
up in our lives as, as much as we strive.
It's really important
to control our emotions.
It's the thing that can take us off the path
very quickly.
[94:2]  ... we unloaded your load ... .
[94:3]  One that burdened your back.
I'm not sure if verse 3 refers to something
in particular or not.
Dr. Khalifa: That's to all of us for our sins.
Catherine: It refers to all of us.
Catherine: We do carry our own, and only God can turn
our sins to credits.
We're told how that can happen, if we sincerely repent and reform
None of us bears the burden of another person, including Jesus, Muhammad, Moses, any of us.
We exalted you to an honorable position.
This is an honorable position.
Sitting on this floor every Friday night is
the most honorable position I've ever been in, in my life.
And that's how I read that verse.
I thought, what tremendous mercy to be led
here and to be allowed to come here every week.
The tremendous responsibility goes with the privilege
and the honor of being here among all of you.
But it's such joy.
I mean, I run here.
I can't wait.
As tired as I am on Fridays when I get home
and I think "oh my gosh, I wonder if I'm gonna get there tonight."
I would walk, I would fly. I even left early tonight.
We, we all do that. This is an exalted position to have access
to the truth, to be here in this close.
Things happen here on a weekly, minute-to-minute,
hour-to-hour basis.
If we're away for one week, and we were talking
about this because we're both gonna be doing that,
how can you dare to miss more than one?
It is horrible, because things are happening so fast.
He's looking at you.
Catherine: So, the, the...
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible)
A woman: IN SHAA ALLAH.
Catherine: The exalted and honorable position is one
where we have certainty.
We're striving towards certainty. We know that God alone is what we're here for.
Our second chance and tremendous, tremendous
mercy.
5 and 6, I have to say this. I liked it better when it said, in every situation there is relief. It was a little softer than
[94:5]  With pain there is gain.
Catherine: However, ...
Dr. Khalifa: I think, I think it's the effect of the gymnasium.
A woman: Yes, no pain, no gain.
Dr. Khalifa: They have a big sign there.
Dr. Khalifa: In every, every corner, everywhere you look, no pain,
no gain.
Dr. Khalifa: I can see it now. It affected me.
Catherine: I'll always, I have to confess, think of it
as with difficulty there is relief.
Dr. Khalifa: That used to be true, though.
For example, you mentioned the mosquitoes
that attacked us on way to San Francisco.
This happens to be one of the most memorable
things, things that
because, mainly because of Douglas Robinson, he was
Praying with us and he was slapping himself so hard,
using both hands, to hit the mosquitoes.
And we, we wanted to laugh, but we couldn't laugh
because we were Praying. There was so much discipline.
Also, we were busy with the mosquitoes.
There was pain, laughter, and reverence, all
at the same time.
And then, we were the fastest creatures on
earth to finish the Prayer.
So, there was pain, there was a lot of pain from that.
Quite an experience.
Dr. Khalifa: And thank God we were all healthy. We didn't get any Encephalitis.
Dr. Khalifa: Excuse me!
A woman: And some of us had rather large
Dr. Khalifa: sores
A woman: thighs or whatever from bites (unintelligible).
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A man: This is (unintelligible)
A man: They do, they like to hurt themselves.
Dr. Khalifa: Please, don't tell us about it. Mahmoud gave us a Khutba about it.
A woman: Yes, we saw it.
Dr. Khalifa: We'll never forget that.
A woman: Not that kind of pain.
Dr. Khalifa: I don't know (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: I don't think it has anything to do with anything in the Quran.
A man: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible) Mahmoud had the video on (unintelligible).